<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM '../../common/dtd/objectweb.dtd'>

<document>
	<properties>
		<author email="joram-team@ow2.org">JORAM team</author>
		<title>Features</title>
		<filename>features.xml</filename>
		<pathtoroot>.</pathtoroot>
	</properties>

	<body>

		<s1 name="JORAM Features">

			<table border="0" width="100%">
				<tr>
					<td align="left" rowspan="2">
						<img src="images/joram.png" alt="JORAM Logo" height="140"
							width="300" border="0" hspace="2" />
					</td>
					<td align="center"></td>
					<td align="right">
						<script type="text/javascript"
							src="http://www.ohloh.net/p/4238/widgets/project_thin_badge.js"></script>
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td align="center"></td>
					<td align="left">
						<p>
							Here's a listing of the main features available in JORAM.
							<br></br>
							For a full description of all features and how to use them, please consult the
							<a href="http://joram.ow2.org/doc/index.html">documentation</a>.
						</p>
					</td>
				</tr>
			</table>

			<s2 name="General">

				<p>
					JORAM fully supports <strong>JMS 1.1</strong> and <strong>Java EE 5</strong> with support
					for transient, persistent, transactional and XA messaging (JORAM provide a fully functional
					XAResource implementation, JORAM sessions can then be enlisted in any JTA transaction acording
					to the normal JTA semantics).
				</p>
				<p>
					All the features described in the JMS 1.1 specification are provided by JORAM.
				</p>
				<p>
					JORAM is an <strong>open-source</strong> software component released under the
					<strong>LGPL</strong> license. JORAM availability on a wide range of Java-based
					platforms - from J2EE<sup>TM</sup> to J2ME<sup>TM</sup> allows your ownership
					investment to be rationalized over your numerous heterogeneous systems and
					Internet devices.
				</p>
				<p>
					JORAM is an <strong>all-in-one</strong> mature messaging solution, it includes many features
					that are missing in competitive offerings and it does not require third-party products, it
					provides a built-in atomic storage and a distributed JNDI server.
					JORAM is shipped with multiples transport implementations: an InVM transport implementation
					for when both the client(s) and server are in the same Java virtual machine, and also a TCP based
					implementation when clients and server are remote.
				</p>
				<p>
					In default configuration it only requires standard JDK classes to run.
				</p>

			</s2>

			<s2 name="Architecture">

				<p>
				<strong>JCA adaptor and seamless integration into Application Server.</strong><br></br>
				JORAM provides a fully functional JCA adaptor that can be used in any JEE compliant application
				server to integrate JORAM so it can be used for consuming messages via Message Driven Beans (MDBs),
				or for sending messages in Enterprise JavaBeans or servlets.<br></br>
				JORAM can easily be installed as the JMS provider of any JCA compliant Application Server. Bu default,
				JORAM is embedded in JOnAS Application Server.<br></br>
				Simple instructions are provided in the distribution showing you how to do this with popular Application Server.
				</p>
				
				<p>
				<strong>Standalone server</strong><br></br>
				JORAM can also be run as a 100% standalone messaging server with no dependencies on Application Server.
				This is of interest if you want messaging, but don't want an application server.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>OSGi Design</strong><br></br>
				Joram is  designed with an OSGiTM based services architecture to provide a dynamically adaptable
				messaging server:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>The Joram server can be launched as a set of OSGi bundles (it is always possible to launch
					the server as a classic Java program).</li>
					<li>Additional services can be started, stopped, reconfigured: Command line interface,
					Web console, etc.</li>
				</ul>

				<p>
				<strong>Embedded server.</strong><br></br>
				JORAM can be configured as a set of Plain Old Java Objects, it can therefore be embedded in any
				third party product and instantiated directly.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Configurable Client/Server communication system.</strong><br></br>
				The JORAM Client/Server transport is configurable and extensible.
				<br></br>
				JORAM is shipped with multiples transport implementations:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li><em>In-VM transport</em> - If client(s) and servers are running in the same Java
					virtual machine, then can be configured to use the InVM tranport which creates direct connections
					in code.
					</li>
					<li><em>TCP or SSL transport</em> - Clients and servers can be configured to communicate using
					standard TCP or encrypted sockets (using the Secure Sockets Layer - SSL).
					</li>
				</ul>

				<p>
				<strong>Very high performance journal for message persistence.</strong><br></br>
				JORAM provides message persistence using its own built-in high performance journal.
				<br></br>
				The JORAM persistence system is completely pluggable, it defines a Service Provider Interface (SPI)
				that you can implement in order to plug-in a new implementation.
				<br></br>
				JORAM is shipped with additionnal persistence modules using relational databases for example.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Fully pluggable transport system for communication between servers.</strong><br></br>
				The JORAM low level transport is completely pluggable, it defines a Service Provider Interface (SPI)
				that you can implement in order to plug-in a new provider.
				<br></br>
				JORAM is shipped with multiples transport implementations:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li><em>TCP transport</em> - Servers can be configured to communicate using standard
					TCP sockets.</li>
					<li><em>SSL transport</em> - Servers can be configured to communicate through encrypted
					TCP sockets using the Secure Sockets Layer (SSL).</li>
					<li><em>HTTP(S) transport</em> - Servers can be configured to communicate messaging traffic
					tunnelling over HTTP(S) requests and responses. This can be useful when you are running through a
					firewall.</li>
					<li><em>UDP transport</em> - Servers can be configured to communicate using UDP sockets.</li>
				</ul>

			</s2>

			<s2 name="Flexible distributed architecture, Load-Balancing and availability">

				<p>
				<strong>Scalability and Distribution.</strong><br></br>
				The combination of the Store and Forward facility with the use of a highly reliable MOM
				provides 100% guaranteed message delivery despite network transient failures or disconnected
				mode.	The fully distributed message broker architecture enables a high level of scalability
				for JORAM systems.
				</p>
				
				<p>
				<strong>Clustered destinations.</strong><br></br>
				A destination, queue or topic, might be distributed among many servers. Such a logical destination
				is made of physical destination representatives on different servers. Such destinations allow both
				a higher degree of availability as well as bandwidth reduction on a wide area network basis.
				<br></br>
				Whereas a regular destination totally depends on the server it is deployed on, a clustered destination
				still works even when some of the servers it is deployed on are down.
				<br></br>
				This feature also allows to spread the inherent load of the transport and processing of messages on
				different servers, reducing the CPU load of each server and the network traffic between servers.
				</p>
				
				<p>
				<strong>Master/Slave high availability server.</strong><br></br>
				If you don't have an existing HA infrastructure, the JORAM Master/Slave configuration is a
				way for providing high availability and fault tolerance to your messaging solution.
				</p>
				
				<p>
				<strong>Replication of data store and Failover via shared file system.</strong><br></br>
				The data store of a live server can be replicated to a backup server, so in event of failure of
				the live server, the data is available immediately for a backup server. The backup server can be
				configured to start from the replicated data store in case of failure of backup server, thus making
				the service available.
				</p>
			
			</s2>

			<s2 name="Management">

				<p>
				Joram includes a distributed management and deployment infrastructure that will dramatically
				simplify your administration operations.
				It provides authentication, authorization, and encryption support that ensure the protection of
				your messages.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>JMX support.</strong><br></br>
				JORAM has extensive support for JMX allowing you to monitor and control the behavior of the
				broker through standard JMX Management facilities.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Administration API and management over JMS connection.</strong><br></br>
				The management API is available using a standard JMS connection, by sending and consuming messages
				to and from a special JMS destination. It allows to remotely manage your distributed JORAM configuration
				through a simple JMS connection.
				<br></br>
				This is over and above the standard functionality available in the JMS 1.1 API which does not define
				a management API.
				</p>
				
				<p>
				<strong>Programmatic creation of connection factories and JMS destinations.</strong><br></br>
				Connection factories, JMS queues and topics can be created programmatically on client side.
				<br></br>
				You are not limited to looking up administered objects via JNDI as per JMS. They can be instantiated
				directly allowing you to remove JNDI from the equation if you do not want to use it.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>XML based scripts for deployment and configuration.</strong><br></br>
				Joram defines a XML scripting language for configuring your application. this allows the deployment
				of all the administered objects of your application without writing a line of code.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Administration console.</strong><br></br>
				A user friendly interface based on GWT (Google Web Toolkit) is now available.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Management destinations.</strong><br></br>
				Management destinations are special destinations producing monitoring messages like number of
				destinations, number of messages in a subscription, etc. You can subscribe to them using the normal
				JMS semantics.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Message counters and statistics.</strong><br></br>
				JORAM message counters allow you to see a history of the messages that arrived in yours destinations
				or subscription over time. It defines several metrics above and beyond a simple message count.
				</p>

			</s2>

			<s2 name="Specialized destinations">

				<p>
				<strong>Hierarchic topics.</strong><br></br>
				Also known as "topic wild-cards", the idea is to build a hierarchical structure of topics.
				<br></br>
				The interest of such a structure is to allow a subscriber to specifically choose the type
				of information it is interested in, by allowing it to subscribe to the corresponding subtopic.
				For example you could create a topic subscriber on <em>news.sports</em> then it will receive all
				messages sent to <em>news.sports.tennis</em> and also <em>news.sports.soccer</em>.
				<br></br>
				To be noted, a hierarchy may be spread over many servers, such a distributed architecture
				introduces flexibility and availability.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Dead message queue.</strong><br></br>
				A dead message queue is a JMS Queue where a message gets sent when it can't be handled normally by
				the system. A dead message is a message considered as undeliverable for various reasons, for example:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>The message can't be delivered after X number of retries.</li>
					<li>The message expires before it is delivered to the client. Not only does JORAM guarantee it
					will never deliver an expired message to a consumer, it also has a configurable garbage collector
					that inspects queues in memory, weeding out expired messages and sending to expiry queues if
					appropriate.
					</li>
					<li>The target destination does not exist or the sender does not have the writing right
					on this target destination.</li>
					<li>The maximum number of messages in the queue has been reached or the message has been
					explicitly deleted on the destination or subscription (a maximum size for a queue or a
					subscription can be configured).
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
				Dead message queue are highly configurable in JORAM - they can be configured either globally or
				individually (User, Destination or subscription).
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Scheduled queue.</strong><br></br>
				A scheduled queue allows to specify time in future when you want message delivered. The message
				won't get delivered until then.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Pluggable acquisition / distribution bridge.</strong><br></br>
				Queue and Topic implements an extension framework for data acquisition (create JMS message from
				external data), and data distribution (create external data from JMS message). JORAM is shipped
				with various acquisition / distribution modules:
				</p>
				
				<ul>
					<li>JMS acquisition / distribution (JMS bridge), 100% once and only once delivery is
					guaranteed with a JMS bridge without having to resort to more heavyweight solutions
					such as JTA (XA). The last implementation (5.5) allows load-balancing and fail-over
					through multiples JMS providers.</li>
					<li>AMQP acquisition / distribution (AMQP bridge since 5.4), the implementation allows
					load-balancing and fail-over through multiples AMQP providers with a 100% once and only
					once delivery guaranteed.</li>
					<li>Mail acquisition / distribution,</li>
					<li>URL acquisition,</li>
					<li>JMX acquisition,</li>
					<li>FTP acquisition / distribution.</li>
				</ul>

			</s2>

			<s2 name="Interoperability and extensibility">

				<p>
				<strong>Support for multi-language clients.</strong><br></br>
				Joram offers a "JMS like" API for C and C++ clients, additionnaly JORAM can be accessed by clients
				in many different languages by using Stomp Connect.
				<br></br>
				JORAM supports the AMQP v0.9.1 specification, later releases of JORAM will provide full AMQP v1 support
				allowing access natively by clients written in many different languages.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>JMS bridge and others.</strong><br></br>
				This allows you to bridge between JORAM and any other JMS 1.1 compliant provider.
				This generic gateway allows JORAM applications to interoperate seamlessly with foreign applications
				running on any JMS compliant messaging service. Additional gateways are also available with AMQP, the
				SMTP mail system and with the FTP file transfer.
				Bridges are highly configurable.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Extensibility.</strong><br></br>
				Queue and Topic implement an extension framework for data acquisition (create JMS message from
				external data), handling, transformation, and data distribution (create external data from JMS message).
				The agent API, available besides the pure JMS API, allows the rapid development of complex distributed
				applications while ensuring full interoperability with JMS applications.
				</p>


			</s2>

			<s2 name="Miscellaneous">

				<p>
				<strong>Transparent auto-reconnection of JMS clients.</strong><br></br>
				Clients can be configured to auto-reconnect to servers when they become unavailable, e.g. due to
				a temporary network problem. Reconnection can be configured with retry-interval, it includes an
				heart-beat mechanism to detect network failures. 
				<br></br>
				Needed data is safely resent in case of failure without running the risk of lost or duplicate
				messages.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Automatic reconnection for inbound connections in JCA Resource Adapter.</strong><br></br>
				Inbound connections will be destroyed and reconnected, if the connection that receives the
				messages fails. This mechanism allows transparent fail-over for MDBs when the JMS provider
				become unavailable, e.g. due to a temporary network problem or perhaps the server is being
				rebooted or has crashed.
				</p>
	
				<p>
				<strong>Configurable message buffering.</strong><br></br>
				Consumers can be configured to buffer messages on the client side to give optimal performance.
				This can also be disabled to give deterministic distribution of messages in a queue with multiple
				consumers.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Producer flow control.</strong><br></br>
				JORAM provides a flow control mechanism to prevent clients overwhelming a server with messages.
				On a per connection basic you can specify the maximum rate, that a producer is allowed to send
				messages at.
				</p>
				
				<p>
				<strong>Implicit acknowledge mode.</strong><br></br>
				With implicit acknowledge mode, messages are acked before delivery, thus avoiding having to ack
				from the client side and reducing the overall traffic on the wire.
				</p>
				
				<p>
				<strong>Non blocking sends.</strong><br></br>
				JORAM can be configured to either send messages blocking or non blocking. With a blocking send (default)
				the call to send() will not return until the message has reached the server.
				</p>

				<p>
				<strong>Pluggable JMS and MOM interceptor.</strong><br></br>
				JORAM defines an interceptor mechanism allowing to transparently process incoming and outgoing
				messages through JMS sessions.<br></br>
				A similar interception mechanism is available for processing messages in the MOM. Interceptors can
				be located on destinations and on connection in/out channels.
				</p>

			</s2>

		</s1>
	</body>
</document>
