<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM '../../common/dtd/objectweb.dtd'>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="joram-team@objectweb.org">joram-team@objectweb.org</author>
    <title>History</title>
    <filename>history.xml</filename>
    <pathtoroot>.</pathtoroot>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <s1 name="JORAM History">

     <subtitle>March 19th, 2003: new JORAM releases.</subtitle>
     <p>JORAM 3.3 is now available as a packaged version.
     As a reminder, it provides a new administration implementation. In CVS it
     is now tagged joram3_3_1. Compared to joram3_3_0, it is a maintenance
     version, correcting a few bugs.
     </p>
     <p>JORAM 3.4 is available only in the CVS distribution. This
     release tagged joram3_4_0 supports the SOAP protocol as a link between
     a Joram client and a Joram platform. It rearchitectures the JMS proxy
     server side, and the JMS connection client side, for supporting multiple 
     protocols (currently TCP and SOAP).</p>
     <hr />

     <subtitle>December 11th, 2002: a new JORAM version tagged 3_3_0 is
      available in the CVS distribution.</subtitle>
      <p>This new version provides a totally refactored <em>administration</em> 
      protocol. Administration is now based on JMS communication and is much
      more flexible than the past implementation. Hopefully it will make
      contributing easier; JORAM's administration still misses graphical tools
      and JMX support, and any contribution would be highly appreciated.
      </p>
      <p>This new administration implementation comes with a new administration
      interface. Old administration codes should go on working even if they now
      use deprecated methods. 
      </p>
      <hr />

     <subtitle>October 21st, 2002: JORAM 3.2 provides new features!</subtitle>
      <p>The main added values of Joram 3.2.0 are the new implementations of
         <em>hierarchical topics</em> and <em>dead message queues</em>.
      </p>
      <p>According to the JMS specification, topics might have a hierarchical
         structure allowing clients to subscribe or publish to given subtopics.
         Joram's fully distributed structure allows a topic hierarchy to be
         spread over many servers.
      </p>
      <p>A dead message queue is a destination getting undeliverable messages.
         Messages might be considered undeliverable because they expired 
         before delivery, because they were sent on a non accessible
         destination or because they are constantly denied when consumed.
      </p>
      <p>This new version also provides a <em>flow control mechanism</em> in
         order to prevent a Joram platform to be overloaded by a heavily
         producing client.
      </p>
      <p><em>Bugs</em> have also been corrected: check the
         <a href="dev/versions.html">versions info</a> page.
      </p> 
      <hr />

      <subtitle>June 18th, 2002: JMS Test Suite tests for JMS 1.1 support!
                </subtitle>
      <p>The <em>JMS Test Suite</em> has its own
         <a href="tests/index.html">page</a>.<br />
	 The suite tests JMS features. All code of the test suite is
	 pure JMS without any dependency to JORAM.
     </p>
     <hr />

     <subtitle>June 10th, 2002: JORAM now implements the new JMS 1.1
        specification!</subtitle>
      <p><em>Joram 3.1.0 fully implements JMS 1.1</em> providing unified
        messaging interfaces for the Point-to-Point and Pub/Sub
        domains. In the previous versions of Joram and JMS, the
        client programming model made a strong distinction between
        these two domains. Now, the domain unification simplifies
        the model and allows to include PTP and Pub/Sub messaging in
        a same transaction.</p>
      <p>No need to modify existing applications: code written for
        the previous Joram and JMS versions will work as is with
        these new versions.</p>
      
      <hr />

      <subtitle>7th june 2002: JORAM 3.0.4 available (cvs tag: joram3_0_4-1)</subtitle>
      
      <p><em>JORAM 3.0.4 is now available for download</em>.<br />
      </p><p>
        This version is a maintenance version of JORAM, it includes
        corrections of bugs in XA and ASF classes. 
        The JORAM CVS repository has been branched after this release:
        next version of JORAM will implement JMS 1.1. The branch
        corresponding to JMS 1.0.2b is jms1_0_2b. 
      </p>

      <hr /> 

      <subtitle>26th March 2002: JORAM 3.0.1 available (cvs tag: joram3_0_1)</subtitle>
      
      <p><em>JORAM 3.0.1 is now available for download</em>.<br />
      </p><p>
	This version corrects all bugs discovered by JORAM community
	since the release of JORAM 3.0.0. These corrections were already available
	in CVS repository.
      </p>

      <hr /> 

      <subtitle>20th March 2002: JMS Test Suite released</subtitle>

      <p><em>A JMS Test Suite</em> has been released under LGPL.<br />
	This suite tests JMS features. All code of the test suite is
	pure JMS without any dependency to JORAM.</p>
      <p>All code is available from JORAM <a
	  href="http://cvs.objectweb.org/cgi-bin/cvsweb/?cvsroot=JORAM">cvs repository</a>. See the test suite
	<a href="http://www.objectweb.org/joram/current/doc/tests/index.html">documentation</a> for more information.</p>

      <hr/>

      <subtitle>11th March 2002: JORAM 3.0.0 available (cvs tag: joram3_0_0)</subtitle>
      
      <p><em>JORAM 3.0.0 is now available for 
	  download</em>. 
      </p><p>
	Compared to JORAM previous versions, this new release is a complete
	re-factoring of the code base. It gets rid of the
	previous limitations and defects. The JMS specification is now fully
	implemented, JORAM provides authentication and security
	features, and introduces a distributed implementation of the Topic
	destination. Its clean and sound code basis guarantees fast
	and easy future developements and enhancements.<br/>
	A suite of tests based on JUnit will be very soon proposed for
	download.
      </p><p>
	Please do not hesitate to keep us informed of any inconsistancy or
	problem you may encounter with the new distribution and documentation.<br />
	We sincerely hope you will enjoy this new version.   
      </p>
      
      <hr />

      <subtitle>16th January 2002: JORAM 2.2 (cvs tag:
	joram2_2)</subtitle>
      <p>This version adds support for <a
	  href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">Ant</a> build
	system. Package are also available for download. Have a look <a
	  href="http://cvs.objectweb.org/cgi-bin/cvsweb/?cvsroot=JORAM">JORAM CVS repository</a>
	<br/>
	Documentation will follow soon...
      </p>

      <hr/>

      <subtitle>14th September 2001: JORAM 2.1.1 (cvs tag: joram2_1_1)</subtitle>
    
      <p>This version corrects some bugs concerning the selectors. <code>Null</code>
      selectors are now authorized, syntax is systematically checked and Strings
      syntax has been enlarged to characters such as '/', ';', ...</p>

      <hr/>

      <subtitle>31st August 2001: JORAM 2.1.0 (cvs tag: joram2_1_0)</subtitle>

      <ul>
	<li><em>New feature:</em> message selection (see JMS spec section 3.8).</li>
	<li><em>Bug:</em> the problem when sending objects not "known" by the agents
	  server inside an ObjectMessage does not occur anymore. No need now to add this
	  object's class in the agents server classpath.</li>
      </ul>
      
      <hr/>
      
      <subtitle>15th May 2001: JORAM 2.0.1 (cvs tag: joram2_0_1)</subtitle>
      
      <p>This version closely follows the 2.0.0 and provides improvements in the
	management of closing sockets, and a better handling of stopping threads when
	closing <code>Sessions</code>, <code>ConnectionConsumers</code> and <code>Connections</code>.</p>
      
      <hr/>
      
      <subtitle>7th May 2001: JORAM 2.0.0 (cvs tag: joram2_0_0) fully implements the
	Application Server Facilities (ASF)</subtitle>
      
      <ul>
	<li><em>New features</em>: ASF part of the specification, synchronous reception on topics
	  and asynchronous reception on queues have been implemented.</li>
	<li>JORAM and JOnAS provide <em>Message Driven Beans</em> support.</li>
	<li><em>Bugs</em> have been fixed: <code>ConnectionFactories</code> accept now more than one active
	  Connection at a time, and problems while running JORAM under Solaris are
	  solved.</li>
      </ul>
      
      <hr/>
      
      <subtitle>5th December 2000: JORAM included in JOnAS</subtitle>
      
      <p>JOnAS tagged <em>2.2.2</em> includes JORAM in its distribution. JOnAS 2.2.2 / JORAM
	1.1.0 allow using JMS from Enterprise Java Beans and have been successfully
	tested on AIX, Linux, Solaris, NT and Windows 2000.</p>
      
      <hr/>
      
      <subtitle>10th October 2000: JORAM is now tagged 1.1.0 (cvs tag: joram1_1_0)</subtitle>
      
      <ul>
	<li><em>New feature:</em> JORAM now includes a <em>JNDI</em> "light" implementation (JNDI 1.1.2).</li>

	<li><em>XA</em> classes have been successfully tested through <connect
	href="../jonas/index.xml">JOnAS</connect> EJB implementation.</li>

	<li>Persistence and lookup <em>bugs</em> fixed.</li>
      </ul>
      
      <hr/>
      <subtitle>31st August 2000 : JORAM implements more</subtitle>
      
      <ul>
	<li><em>XA</em> classes, allowing JMS operations to be involved in a distributed
	  transaction, are available.</li>
	<li><em>Transacted</em> mode completed.</li>
	<li>External <em>JNDI</em> now usable.</li>
      </ul>
      
      <hr/>

      <subtitle>26th May 2000 : JORAM first open source version available !</subtitle>
      
    </s1>
  </body>

</document>
