<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM '../../common/dtd/objectweb.dtd'>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="joram-team@objectweb.org">joram-team@objectweb.org</author>
    <title>History</title>
    <filename>history.xml</filename>
    <pathtoroot>.</pathtoroot>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <s1 name="JORAM History">

      <subtitle>19th March 2002: JORAM 3.0.1 available (cvs tag: joram3_0_1)</subtitle>
      
      <p><em>JORAM 3.0.1 is now available for <a
	  href="http://www.objectweb.org/joram/download/">
	  download</a></em>. <a href="http://www.objectweb.org/joram/doc/">Documentation</a> has also been
	updated..<br />
      </p><p>
	This version corrects all bugs discovered by JORAM community
	since the release of JORAM 3.0.0. which were already available
	in CVS repository.
      </p>

      <hr /> 

      <subtitle>20th March 2002: JMS Test Suite released</subtitle>

      <p>A JMS Test Suite has been released under LGPL.<br />
	This suite tests JMS features. All code of the test suite is
	pure JMS without any dependency to JORAM.</p>
      <p>All code is available from JORAM <a
	  href="http://cvs.objectweb.org/cgi-bin/cvsweb/?cvsroot=JORAM">cvs repository</a>. See the test suite
	<a href="http://www.objectweb.org/joram/current/doc/tests/index.html">documentation</a> for more information.</p>

      <hr/>

      <subtitle>11th March 2002: JORAM 3.0.0 available (cvs tag: joram3_0_0)</subtitle>
      
      <p><em>JORAM 3.0.0 is now available for <a
	  href="http://www.objectweb.org/joram/download/">
	  download</a></em>. <a href="http://www.objectweb.org/joram/doc/">Documentation</a> has also been
	updated and new samples are provided.<br />
      </p><p>
	Compared to JORAM previous versions, this new release is a complete
	re-factoring of the code base. It gets rid of the
	previous limitations and defects. The JMS specification is now fully
	implemented, JORAM provides authentication and security
	features, and introduces a distributed implementation of the Topic
	destination. Its clean and sound code basis guarantees fast
	and easy future developements and enhancements.<br/>
	A suite of tests based on JUnit will be very soon proposed for
	download.
      </p><p>
	Please do not hesitate to keep us informed of any inconsistancy or
	problem you may encounter with the new distribution and documentation.<br />
	We sincerely hope you will enjoy this new version.   
      </p>
      
      <hr />

      <subtitle>6th March 2002: </subtitle>
      
      <p>The new version of JORAM will be commited in CVS. Since this
      version is a complete rewrite of JORAM, some problems may occur
      when commiting into CVS. CVS may be in a inconstitent state for
      the next two days. Thus we recommend anyone using CVS to avoid
      to checkout JORAM for the next two days. As soon as the CVS is
      ok, we will warn you.
      </p>

      <hr />
      <subtitle>1st March 2002: new version of JORAM to be expected soon</subtitle>

      <p>A new version of JORAM will soon be available (likely next week). JORAM 3.0 is a
      complete refactoring of JORAM with better conformance,
      scalability and performance. It should also be integrated with
      the next version of JOnAS. Stay tuned for future information.
      </p>
      
      <hr /> 

      <subtitle>16th January 2002: Documentation update</subtitle>
      <p>The <a
	  href="http://www.objectweb.org/joram/current/doc/install/index.html">Installation guide</a> 
	has been updated to take into account Ant support.</p>

      <hr/>
      
      <subtitle>16th January 2002: JORAM 2.2 (cvs tag:
	joram2_2)</subtitle>
      <p>This version adds support for <a
	  href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">Ant</a> build
	system. Package are also available for download. Have a look <a
	  href="http://cvs.objectweb.org/cgi-bin/cvsweb/?cvsroot=JORAM">JORAM CVS repository</a>
	<br/>
	Documentation will follow soon...
      </p>

      <hr/>

      <subtitle>Documentation</subtitle>
      
      <p>Documentation is now made in 
	<a href="http://www.docbook.org">DocBook</a>. You can now download
	all <a href="doc/index.html">JORAM documentation</a> in PostScript or PDF (it is still
	available online in HTML).</p>
      
      <hr/>

      <subtitle>14th September 2001: JORAM 2.1.1 (cvs tag: joram2_1_1)</subtitle>
    
      <p>This version corrects some bugs concerning the selectors. <code>Null</code>
      selectors are now authorized, syntax is systematically checked and Strings
      syntax has been enlarged to characters such as '/', ';', ...</p>

      <hr/>

      <subtitle>31st August 2001: JORAM 2.1.0 (cvs tag: joram2_1_0)</subtitle>

      <ul>
	<li><em>New feature:</em> message selection (see JMS spec section 3.8).</li>
	<li><em>Bug:</em> the problem when sending objects not "known" by the agents
	  server inside an ObjectMessage does not occur anymore. No need now to add this
	  object's class in the agents server classpath.</li>
      </ul>
      
      <hr/>
      
      <subtitle>15th May 2001: JORAM 2.0.1 (cvs tag: joram2_0_1)</subtitle>
      
      <p>This version closely follows the 2.0.0 and provides improvements in the
	management of closing sockets, and a better handling of stopping threads when
	closing <code>Sessions</code>, <code>ConnectionConsumers</code> and <code>Connections</code>.</p>
      
      <hr/>
      
      <subtitle>7th May 2001: JORAM 2.0.0 (cvs tag: joram2_0_0) fully implements the
	Application Server Facilities (ASF)</subtitle>
      
      <ul>
	<li><em>New features</em>: ASF part of the specification, synchronous reception on topics
	  and asynchronous reception on queues have been implemented.</li>
	<li>JORAM and JOnAS provide <em>Message Driven Beans</em> support.</li>
	<li><em>Bugs</em> have been fixed: <code>ConnectionFactories</code> accept now more than one active
	  Connection at a time, and problems while running JORAM under Solaris are
	  solved.</li>
      </ul>
      
      <hr/>
      
      <subtitle>5th December 2000: JORAM included in JOnAS</subtitle>
      
      <p>JOnAS tagged <em>2.2.2</em> includes JORAM in its distribution. JOnAS 2.2.2 / JORAM
	1.1.0 allow using JMS from Enterprise Java Beans and have been successfully
	tested on AIX, Linux, Solaris, NT and Windows 2000.</p>
      
      <hr/>
      
      <subtitle>10th October 2000: JORAM is now tagged 1.1.0 (cvs tag: joram1_1_0)</subtitle>
      
      <ul>
	<li><em>New feature:</em> JORAM now includes a <em>JNDI</em> "light" implementation (JNDI 1.1.2).</li>

	<li><em>XA</em> classes have been successfully tested through <connect
	href="../jonas/index.xml">JOnAS</connect> EJB implementation.</li>

	<li>Persistence and lookup <em>bugs</em> fixed.</li>
      </ul>
      
      <hr/>
      <subtitle>31st August 2000 : JORAM implements more</subtitle>
      
      <ul>
	<li><em>XA</em> classes, allowing JMS operations to be involved in a distributed
	  transaction, are available.</li>
	<li><em>Transacted</em> mode completed.</li>
	<li>External <em>JNDI</em> now usable.</li>
      </ul>
      
      <hr/>

      <subtitle>26th May 2000 : JORAM first open source version available !</subtitle>
      
    </s1>
  </body>

</document>
