<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM '../../common/dtd/objectweb.dtd'>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="joram-team@ow2.org">JORAM team</author>
    <title>Home Page</title>
    <filename>index.xml</filename>
    <pathtoroot>.</pathtoroot>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <s1 name="JORAM: Java (TM) Open Reliable Asynchronous Messaging">

    <table border="0" width="100%">
  	<tr>
	    <td align="left" rowspan="2">
	      <img src="images/joram.png" alt="JORAM Logo" height="140" width="300" border="0" hspace="2"/>
      </td>
	    <td align="center"></td>
	    <td align="right"><script type="text/javascript" src="http://www.ohloh.net/p/4238/widgets/project_thin_badge.js"></script></td>
	  </tr>
  	<tr>
	    <td align="center"></td>
	    <td align="left">
	      <p>JORAM has been made available for download since May 2000.<br></br>
        As a standalone software, JORAM has been downloaded more than 100,000 times.</p>
	    </td>
	  </tr>
    </table>
    
    </s1>
      
    <s1 name="Introduction">
      
      <p><strong>JORAM</strong> incorporates a 100% pure Java implementation of <strong>JMS 1.1</strong>
      (Java Message Service API released by Sun Microsystem, Inc.) specification.<br></br>
      It provides access to a really distributed MOM (Message Oriented Middleware), built on top of the
      <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/">ScalAgent D.T.</a> agents based platform.</p>
      
      <p>JORAM is a mature project started in 1999, it is an <strong>open source</strong> software released under
      the <strong>LGPL</strong> license since May 2000.<br></br>
      It provides a production ready distributed MOM already used within many critical operational applications.</p>

      <p>Stable versions of JORAM are JMS 1.1 certified. Moreover JORAM is used by JOnAS to undergo the J2EE 1.4 certification,
      and has passed all tests concerning JMS 1.1 certification in this J2EE TCK.<br></br>
      Professional Support is available from <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/products/joram-support.htm">Scalagent D.T.</a>.</p>
 
    </s1>
   
    <s1 name="Latest News">
      
	    <s2 name="December 2nd and 3rd, 2009: JORAM Training Session, Grenoble, France">
	      <p>A two-day training session about JORAM is scheduled in Grenoble; it will be delivered in french language.</p>
	      <p>The session is entitled "Design and Deploy a Distributed JORAM Messaging System".</p>
	      <p>This training session is targeted at architects and system designers that intend to integrate  the JORAM component
	      within a global distributed solution. It includes a significant part of  experimentations and case studies based on
	      real-world application scenarios.</p>
	      <p>The session is conducted by ScalAgent Distributed Technologies, the leading developer of the JORAM component. We
	      offer to share our expertise through a training session aiming at providing the key knowledge to use and deploy a JORAM
	      system that fits your own requirements. This two-day session details the design principles of JORAM and describes the
	      best practices that will enable to take advantage of its advanced properties for complex networked environments.</p>
	      <p>Detailed information about this training session is available online
	      <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/fr/datasheet/091202-JORAM-formation.pdf ">(PDF, in french only)</a></p>
      </s2>
 
      <s2 name="September 21, 2009: JORAM 5.2.5 is released">
      <p>This version is available for <a href="http://joram.ow2.org/download/index.html">download</a>, and in Maven repository.</p>
      <p>It introduces some improvements and bug fixes.</p>
      <p>This version is bundled in <a href="http://jonas.ow2.org/">Jonas</a> 4.10.5 and 5.1.0.</p>
      <p>It is tagged in SVN (JORAM_5_2_5), the complete list of changes can be viewed either in
      <a href="http://joram.ow2.org/dev/versions.html">code updates</a> or in
      <a href="http://svn.forge.objectweb.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/joram/trunk/joram/history">SVN history</a>.</p>
      </s2>
			
      <s2 name="January 18, 2006">
        <p>JORAM is acknowledged as the best open source MOM implementation, according to
        <a href="http://jdj.sys-con.com/read/171303_3.htm">JDJ's readers</a>, challenging
        proprietary products from IBM, Sun and TIBCO.</p>
      </s2>

	    <s2 name="September 26th, 2005: JORAM Survey Synthesis">
	      <p>A synthesis of the JORAM Survey is available <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/datasheet/050926-JORAM_Survey-Synthesis.pdf">here</a>.</p>
 	      <p>Several users have expressed their need for various forms of services (support, consulting, training, etc.).
        Therefore we would like to remind that a description of professional services on JORAM is available 
        <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/products/joram-overview.htm">here</a>.
        Do not hesitate to contact us for any further question you may have on JORAM :
        <a href="mailto:contact@scalagent.com">contact@scalagent.com</a>.</p>
      </s2>

      <subtitle><a href="http://joram.ow2.org/history.html">All the News</a></subtitle>
    </s1>

  </body>
</document>
