<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM '../../common/dtd/objectweb.dtd'>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="joram-team@objectweb.org">JORAM team</author>
    <title>Home Page</title>
    <filename>index.xml</filename>
    <pathtoroot>.</pathtoroot>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <s1 name="JORAM: Java (TM) Open Reliable Asynchronous Messaging">

      <subtitle>As a standalone software, JORAM has been downloaded
                more than 22,000 times</subtitle>

      <table border="0">
	<tr>
	  <td><img src="images/joram.jpg" alt="JORAM logo" height="132"
               width="287" border="0" hspace="2"/></td>
	  <td valign="middle"></td>
	</tr>
      </table>
      
      <p><strong>JORAM</strong> incorporates a 100% pure Java
      implementation of <strong>JMS</strong> (Java Message Service API
      released by Sun Microsystem, Inc.). It provides access to a MOM
      (Message Oriented Middleware), built on top of the <a
      href="http://www.scalagent.com/">ScalAgent</a> agents based
      distributed platform.</p>
      <p> JORAM is an <strong>open source</strong> software released under
      the <strong>LGPL</strong> license.</p>
   
      <s2 name="Latest News">

	<subtitle>May 13, 2005: JORAM 4.2.3 maintenanece release and 4.3 preview</subtitle>
	<p>The JORAM 4.2.3 maintenance release is now available for download. It basically includesd bug fixes, the complete list is available in the <a href="dev/version.html">Code Update</a> page. </p>
	<p>The next JORAM 4.3 version will include new features :</p>
	<ul>
	  <li>JMX management improved and extended</li>
	  <li>Performances improvments</li>
	  <li>Handling of large message transmission( called swap out mode)</li>
	  <li>Complete SSL support with handling of encrypted client to server communications</li>
	</ul>


	<subtitle>March 31, 2005: JORAM 4.2 final release is available</subtitle>
	<p>The Joram 4.2 release features high availability, enhanced management facilities and improved performances.
        </p>
	<ul>
	  <li><strong>High Availability</strong> Joram 4.2 provides the active replication of Joram servers and 
          underlying agent servers, as well as replicated JORAM clients. It transparently handles network handover 
          and server failover. This version currently relies on the use of  JGroups.</li>
	  <li><strong>Dynamic Configuration</strong> Joram 4.2 provide facilities to remotely add and remove Joram
          servers dynamically, using the Joram Administration API. This key feature, combined with upgraded JMX 
          implementation, initiates a new set of management facilities for Joram.</li>
	  <li><strong>Upgraded JMX management</strong></li>
	  <li><strong>Architecture and Performance improvements</strong>. Joram V4.2 provides a packaged version of
          a wide set of deep changes within the Joram and underlying bus architectures that lead to performance 
          improvements compared to prior version V4.1. Communication protocols are concerned by this evolution, thus 
          preventing backward compatibility with prior Joram versions.</li>
	  <li><strong>JDK 1.5 support</strong></li>
	</ul>

        <p>This version has been partly sponsored by France Telecom R&amp;D</p>
	<p> Sponsoring helps maintain a high quality message oriented middleware available to the community and makes
        its constant evolution a reality that anyone can benefit from. Contact the joram-team@objectweb.org if you want
        to participate and sustain the shared development effort of JORAM as the enterprise-class alternative to 
        proprietary messaging system.</p>

	<subtitle>September 14, 2004: JORAM 4.1 is available</subtitle>
	<p>Joram 4.1 is finally available for download. It provides the following new features as well
			 as fixes and improvements : </p>
	<ul>
	  <li>The Joram 4.1 JCA 1.5 RA, handles:
	    <ul>
	      <li>Inbound (asynchronous message flow) and Outbound (synchronous message flow) communications</li>
	      <li>Support of distributed (XA) and local transactions.</li>
	      <li>Automatic recovery of indoubt Xids via XAResource.recover().</li> 
	      <li>Deployment as a Resource Adapter to an external JORAM server.</li>
	      <li>Deployment in collocated mode : a JORAM server is started and stopped at RA deployment and undeployment.
	      </li>
	    </ul>
	  </li>
	  <li>The clustered queue feature provides a load-balancing mechanism. It is made up of several queues
	   exchanging messages depending on their load. This new feature is sponsored by France Telecom R&amp;D,
	   as will be the future High-Availability Joram server to be released in the next version. </li>
	</ul>
	<p>JORAM 4.1 is used by JOnAS to undergo the J2EE 1.4 certification, and has already passed all tests 
	  concerning JMS in this TCK.</p>
	<p>The new packages are available in the <a href="download/index.html">download area</a>. The CVS tag is 
	 joram4_1_0 (<a href="http://forge.objectweb.org/cvs/?group_id=4">CVS repository</a>).</p>
	<p>The documentation has also been deeply updated with a new all-in-one manual.</p>
		
    </s2>
    </s1>

    
  </body>

</document>
