<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM '../../common/dtd/objectweb.dtd'>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="joram-team@ow2.org">JORAM team</author>
    <title>Specification</title>
    <filename>technical.xml</filename>
    <pathtoroot>.</pathtoroot>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <s1 name="JORAM: Java (TM) Open Reliable Asynchronous Messaging">

      <subtitle>As a standalone software, JORAM has been downloaded
                more than 22,000 times</subtitle>

      <table border="0">
      <tr>
        <td><img src="images/joram.jpg" alt="JORAM logo" height="132" width="287" border="0" hspace="2"/></td>
	      <td valign="middle"></td>
      </tr>
      </table>
      
      <p><strong>JORAM</strong> incorporates a 100% pure Java implementation of <strong>JMS</strong>
      (Java Message Service API released by Sun Microsystem, Inc.). It provides access to a MOM
      (Message Oriented Middleware), built on top of the <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/">ScalAgent D.T.</a>
      agents based distributed platform.</p>
      <p> JORAM is an <strong>open source</strong> software released under the <strong>LGPL</strong> license.</p>

      <s2 name="Specification">

        <p>JORAM provides full support to <strong>JMS 1.1</strong>:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Unified interfaces for the Point-to-Point (PTP) and
            Publish/Subscribe (Pub/Sub) messaging models</li>
          <li><strong>AND</strong> still the semantically specific PTP and
            Pub/Sub interfaces</li>
          <li>Full backward compatibility with JMS 1.0.2b compliant
            applications</li>
          <li>Local, TCP and SOAP (HTTP/XML) client-server communication
              protocols</li>
          <li>Message persistence and guarantee of delivery</li>
          <li>Hierarchical topics</li>
          <li>Message selection</li>
          <li>Message prioritization</li>
          <li>A JCA 1.5 Resource Adapter</li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>JORAM also includes the following extra-features:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>A persistent, reliable and distributed JNDI server</li>
          <li>A configurable dead message queue</li>
          <li>Load balancing through clustered topics and queues</li>
          <li>Monitoring methods</li>
          <li>A bridge feature allowing to link JORAM to any JMS compliant messaging platform</li>
          <li>Client libraries allowing J2ME applications to access the JORAM platform in a JMS 1.1 "way"</li>
          <li>Client libraries allowing C or C++ applications to access the JORAM platform in a JMS 1.1 "way"</li>
          <li>High Availability provides the active replication of Joram servers and underlying agent servers,
          as well as replicated JORAM clients. It transparently handles network handover and server failover.
          This version currently relies on the use of  JGroups.</li>
          <li>Dynamic Configuration provides facilities to remotely add and remove Joram servers dynamically
          through the Administration API of JORAM. This great feature, combined with updated JMX implementation,
          initiates a new set of  management facilities in JORAM.</li>
        </ul>
      </s2>

      <s2 name="Getting Involved">
	
      <p>Any input or personal view for improving and/or developing JORAM is welcome. JORAM, as an
      <strong>open source</strong> project, also welcomes <strong>external contributions</strong>.
      Interested? Contact <a href="mailto:joram-team@ow2.org">us</a> or check the
      <a href="dev/corner.html">developer's corner</a>.</p>

      </s2>  
    </s1>
  </body>
</document>
