<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM '../../../common/dtd/objectweb.dtd'>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="joram-team@ow2.org">JORAM team</author>
    <title>Download</title>
    <filename>index.xml</filename>
    <pathtoroot>..</pathtoroot>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <s1 name="Downloading...">
      <s2 name="JORAM source and binary packages">
	<p>The JORAM source and binary packages are available from the
        ObjectWeb Forge file repository page.</p>
      
	<p>The latest release packages are:</p>
	<ul>
	  <li><code>joram-5.*.tgz</code>, including JORAM client and MOM
        libraries, the graphical tool library, the J2ME kJORAM client library and the JORAM
        samples sources;</li>
	  <li><code>joram-5.*-src.tgz</code>, including JORAM client and MOM
        sources, the graphical tool sources, the J2ME kJORAM client sources and the JORAM samples
        sources;</li>
	  <li><code>joram-jonasadapter-5.*.rar</code> ,JCA Adapter for Jonas </li>
	  <li><code>joram-raconfig-5.*.tgz</code>, facilities enabling configuration of JCA rars.</li>
	  <li><code>joram-5.*-RA.rar</code>, the resource adapter for a collocated JORAM server within any J2EE 1.4 compliant 
		application server.</li>
	  <li><code>joram-5.*-remoteRA.rar</code>, the resource adapter for any J2EE 1.4 application server with a non collocated 
		JORAM server (possibly running remotely).</li>
	</ul>
 
	<p>The license agreement is displayed before the download can start.
      <a href="http://forge.objectweb.org/project/showfiles.php?group_id=4">
      Click here to start the download process</a>.</p>
	
	<p>Note: all the packages are available as .tgz files. To unzip these
      files, just go where you want to install JORAM, and unzip it. You can
      use gunzip and tar tools on unix-like systems, or winzip utility on
      Windows. Please consult the <strong>
      JORAM documentation</strong> for installation instructions and a tutorial.</p>
      </s2>

      <s2 name="JORAM CVS code base">
	<p>For getting the latest stable JORAM version, or for the current
    development release, you have to use <a href="http://forge.objectweb.org/cvs/?group_id=4">CVS</a>.</p>

	<p>JORAM and kJORAM are available by checking out the <strong>joram</strong> module.</p>

	<p>The latest stable release tag is <strong>JORAM_5_0_9</strong>. For 
    getting the current development release (potentially unstable), check
    out joram with no tag.</p>
        <p>A snapshot is generated each day at 00:00 AM CEST: <a href="http://forge.objectweb.org/cvssnapshots/joram-cvs-latest.tar.gz">Download the last CVS snapshot</a>.</p>
      </s2>
    </s1>
  </body>
</document>
