<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM '../../common/dtd/objectweb.dtd'>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="joram-team@ow2.org">JORAM team</author>
    <title>History</title>
    <filename>oldhistory.xml</filename>
    <pathtoroot>.</pathtoroot>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <s1 name="JORAM History">

      <subtitle>May 13, 2005: JORAM 4.2.3 maintenance release and 4.3 preview</subtitle>
      <p>The JORAM 4.2.3 maintenance release is now available for download. It basically includes
           bug fixes, their complete list is available in the 
           <a href="dev/versions.html">Code Update</a> page. </p>
      <p>The next JORAM 4.3 version will include new features :</p>
      <ul>
      <li>JMX management improved and extended</li>
      <li>Performance improvements</li>
      <li>Handling of large message transmission (called swap out mode)</li>
      <li>Complete SSL support with handling of encrypted client to server communications</li>
      </ul>
    
      <subtitle>March 31, 2005: JORAM 4.2 final release is available</subtitle>
      <p>The Joram 4.2 release features high availability, enhanced management facilities and improved performances.
        </p>
	<ul>
	  <li><strong>High Availability</strong> Joram 4.2 provides the active replication of Joram servers and 
          underlying agent servers, as well as replicated JORAM clients. It transparently handles network handover 
          and server failover. This version currently relies on the use of  JGroups.</li>
	  <li><strong>Dynamic Configuration</strong> Joram 4.2 provide facilities to remotely add and remove Joram
          servers dynamically, using the Joram Administration API. This key feature, combined with upgraded JMX 
          implementation, initiates a new set of management facilities for Joram.</li>
	  <li><strong>Upgraded JMX management</strong></li>
	  <li><strong>Architecture and Performance improvements</strong>. Joram V4.2 provides a packaged version of
          a wide set of deep changes within the Joram and underlying bus architectures that lead to performance 
          improvements compared to prior version V4.1. Communication protocols are concerned by this evolution, thus 
          preventing backward compatibility with prior Joram versions.</li>
	  <li><strong>JDK 1.5 support</strong></li>
	</ul>

        <p>This version has been partly sponsored by France Telecom R&amp;D</p>
      <p> Sponsoring helps maintain a high quality message oriented middleware available to the community and makes
        its constant evolution a reality that anyone can benefit from. Contact the joram-team@ow2.org if you want
        to participate and sustain the shared development effort of JORAM as the enterprise-class alternative to 
        proprietary messaging system.</p>

      <subtitle>March 11,2005: JORAM 4.2 release candidate 2 is available.</subtitle>
      <p>The JORAM 4.2 RC2 contains mainly bug and fixes along with upgraded JMX management facilites.</p>

      <subtitle>January 10, 2005: JORAM 4.2 release candidate 1 is available</subtitle>
      <p>Joram 4.2 RC1 provides new features as high-availability, dynamic configuration, 
        and a lot of fixes and improvements.</p>
	<ul>
	  <li><strong>High Availability</strong> Joram V4.2 provides the active replication of Joram servers and 
          underlying agent servers, as well as replicated JORAM clients. It transparently handles network handover 
          and server failover. This version currently relies on the use of  JGroups.</li>
	  <li><strong>Dynamic Configuration</strong> Joram V4.2 provide facilities to remotely add and remove Joram
          servers dynamically, using the Joram Administration API. This key feature, combined with upgraded JMX 
          implementation, initiates a new set of management facilities for Joram.</li>
	  <li><strong>Architecture and Performance improvements</strong>. Joram V4.2 provides a packaged version of
          a wide set of deep changes within the Joram and underlying bus architectures that lead to performance 
          improvements compared to prior version V4.1. Communication protocols are concerned by this evolution, thus 
          preventing backward compatibility with prior Joram versions.</li>
	</ul>
        <p>This version has been sponsored by France Telecom R&amp;D</p>
      <p> Sponsoring helps maintain a high quality message oriented middleware available to the community and makes
        its constant evolution a reality that anyone can benefit from. Contact the joram-team@ow2.org if you want
        to participate and sustain the shared development effort of JORAM as the enterprise-class alternative to 
        proprietary messaging system.</p>

      <subtitle>January 7, 2005: JORAM 4.1.5 maintenance release is available</subtitle>
      <p>Joram 4.1.5 is a maintenance release with bug fixes and configuration improvements.</p>

      <subtitle>December 22,2004: JORAM 4.1.4 maintenance release is available</subtitle>
      <p>Joram 4.1.4 is a maintenance release with bug fixes and configuration improvements.</p>

      <subtitle>December 2004: New suite of professional services on JORAM</subtitle>
      <p>Please check the <a href="support.html">Joram Support pages</a> or <a href="http://www.scalagent.com">ScalAgent website</a>.</p>

      <subtitle>November 9, 2004: JORAM 4.1.2 maintenance release is available</subtitle>
      <p>Joram 4.1.2 is a maintenance release with bug fixes and performance improvements. This version is embedded in the last JOnAS build (4.2.0)</p>

      <subtitle>October 13, 2004: JORAM 4.1.1 maintenance release is available</subtitle>
      <p>Joram 4.1.1 is a maintenance release with bug fixes and updates of the underlying network communication system.</p>

      <subtitle>September 14, 2004: JORAM 4.1 is available</subtitle>
      <p>Joram 4.1 is finally available for download. It provides the following new features as well
	 as fixes and improvements : </p>
      <ul>
	<li>The Joram 4.1 JCA 1.5 RA, handles:
	  <ul>
	    <li>Inbound (asynchronous message flow) and Outbound (synchronous message flow) communications</li>
	    <li>Support of distributed (XA) and local transactions.</li>
	    <li>Automatic recovery of indoubt Xids via XAResource.recover().</li> 
	    <li>Deployment as a Resource Adapter to an external JORAM server.</li>
	    <li>Deployment in collocated mode : a JORAM server is started and stopped at RA deployment and undeployment.</li>
	  </ul>
	</li>
	<li>The clustered queue feature provides a load-balancing mechanism. It is made up of several queues
	exchanging messages depending on their load. This new feature is sponsored by France Telecom R&amp;D,
	as will be the future High-Availability Joram server to be released in the next version. </li>
      </ul>
      <p>JORAM 4.1 is used by JOnAS to undergo the J2EE 1.4 certification, and has already passed all tests 
	concerning JMS in this TCK.</p>
      <p>The new packages are available in the <a href="download/index.html">download area</a>. The CVS tag is 
	joram4_1_0 (<a href="http://forge.objectweb.org/cvs/?group_id=4">CVS repository</a>).</p>
      <p>The documentation has also been deeply updated with a new all-in-one manual.</p>

      <subtitle>October 20-21: JORAM Training Session, Grenoble, France</subtitle>
      <p>A two-day training session on JORAM is scheduled and will be delivered in french language.
	The session is entitled "Design and Deploy a Distributed JORAM Messaging System".</p>
      <p>This training session is targeted at architects and system designers that intend to integrate 
	the JORAM component within a global distributed solution. It includes a significant part of 
	experimentations and case studies based on real-world application scenarios.</p>
      <p>The session is conducted by ScalAgent Distributed Technologies, the leading developer 
	of the JORAM component. We offer to share our expertise through a training session that provides
	 the key knowledge to use and deploy a JORAM system that fits your requirements.
	This two-day session details the design principles of JORAM and describes the best practices 
	to take advantage of its advanced properties in complex networked environments.</p>
      <p>Detailed information about this training session is available online 
	<a href="http://www.scalagent.com/spip.php?article314">(PDF, in french only)</a></p>

      <subtitle>July 1st, 2004: Report of the 1st JORAM Users' Day</subtitle>
      <p>The first JORAM Users' Day has been held last June 17 th in Paris.
	 This event was the first successful attempt within the ObjectWeb community 
	 to have direct exchanges between users and designers/developers of an 
	 ObjectWeb component.</p>
      <p>The Report as well as some of the presentations are available online at
	  the ScalAgent Distributed Technologies web site : </p>
      <ul>
	<li>Report as <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/products/joram-userday040617-report.htm">HTML</a>
	  or <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/datasheet/040617-JORAM-Day-report.pdf">PDF</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/datasheet/040617-JoramDay-Intro-UK.pdf">
	 Introduction by Roland Balter (ScalAgent Distributed Technologies)(PDF)</a>
	 </li>
	<li><a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/datasheet/040617-ObjectWeb-Joram.pdf">
	Next Generation Open Source by J.P. Laisné (President of the 
	 Objectweb consortium)(PDF in french)</a>
	 </li>
       <li><a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/datasheet/040617-EPFL-joram_day.pdf">
	 JMSGroups: Towards JMS-Compliant Group Communication by A. Kupsys 
	 (EPFL Switzerland) (PDF)</a>
	 </li>
      </ul>
      <p>The discussion about JORAM is open especially for those who have not been
	 able to join the Users' Day. Any contribution is welcome on the main
	 JORAM mailing list.</p>		 

      <subtitle>May 3, 2004: JORAM users' day announcement</subtitle>
      <p>ObjectWeb and the JORAM core development team are setting up
      a JORAM Users' Day on June 17th in Paris (place to be defined later).</p>
      <p>This day is intended to be the first attempt of direct exchanges
      between members of the JORAM community. The meeting is an opportunity
      to report on the credibility of the JORAM solution and to raise
      questions and answers about the durability and evolution of this open
      source product.</p>
      <p>Details about the JORAM Users Day can be found
      <a href="current/doc/JORAM-Day.pdf">here</a>.</p>
      <p>A french version of this annoucement is also available at:
      <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/fr/products/joram-usergroup.htm">
      http://www.scalagent.com/pages/fr/products/joram-usergroup.htm</a>.</p>
			
      <subtitle>February 13, 2004: JORAM 4.0 is released and provides major
      new features!</subtitle>
      <p>JORAM 4.0 is the first release of a new JORAM generation with even
      more features and architecturing capabilities.</p>
      <p>This new version introduces the following new
      functionnalities:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Collocated communication protocol</strong>: when a client
        and its JORAM server run collocated in a same JVM, they may now
        communicate through a "local" optimised connection rather than a 
        TCP connection. This feature will highly impact the use of JORAM with
        JOnAS for example, when set as collocated.</li>
      </ul>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Distributed JNDI server</strong>: this latest version of
        JORAM's naming server may now be deployed on many JORAM servers, 
        so that naming information is accessible from multiple points. 
        Client applications do not depend anymore on a single central JNDI
        server.</li>
      </ul>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Universal JMS bridge</strong>: JORAM may be configured
        for establishing a link to any JMS compliant foreign JMS provider.
        This feature allows JORAM client applications to actually communicate
        with foreign JMS destinations totally transparently.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><strong>Administration methods</strong> have been largely 
      modified for simplifying the evolution of management following
      the new JORAM releases. Old admin and monitoring classes
      have been kept but this will be temporary.</p>
      <p>This new version also introduces a <strong>new sources
      tree</strong>, which may be quickly described as follows:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><code>com/scalagent</code>: sources of the kJoram client
        layer</li> 
        <li><code>fr/dyade/</code>: sources of the agent platform</li>
        <li><code>org/objectweb/joram</code>: sources of the MOM and JORAM
        client layers</li>
      </ul>
      <p>New packages have been released, the CVS tag is
      <strong>joram4_0_0</strong>.</p>

      <subtitle>November 7, 2003: the first major
      contribution from JORAM ever growing community</subtitle>
      <p>JORAM 3.7 includes the long expected graphical tool for
      administering and monitoring the state of a JORAM platform.
      Thanks to Alexander Fedorowicz, an active contributor, this tool is
      made available to the whole JORAM community.</p>
      <p>The tool allows to administer and monitor a JORAM platform made of
      one or many interconnected JORAM servers. It allows to create and delete
      destinations, users, and also to bind them to JORAM's naming server.</p>
      <p>The tool sources are available in CVS and in the sources package. It
      is provided as an independent library in the binary distribution.
      </p>
      <p>This latest release is also available through a CVS checkout, tag
        <strong>joram3_7_0</strong>.</p>

      <subtitle>August 7, 2003: JORAM 3.6 connects J2ME devices!</subtitle>
      <p>JORAM 3.6 follows the 3.4 release in addressing the opening of the
      JORAM platform to <strong>heterogenous</strong> client applications. Where
      JORAM 3.4, with the support of SOAP as client communication protocol,
      opened the platform to non-Java applications, the 3.6 release, with
      its new kJORAM libraries, allows J2ME applications to use JORAM messaging
      functionnalities. A J2ME application is a lightweight Java application
      deployed and running on a mobile device such as a PDA or a smart
      phone.</p>
      <p>kJORAM is available in specific packages and also by checking out
      the <strong>joram</strong> CVS module, tag <strong>joram3_6_0</strong>.
      </p>

      <subtitle>June 24th, 2003: JORAM 3.5 is available.</subtitle>
      <p>JORAM 3.5 is available in the CVS repository (joram3_5_0 tag) as well
      as packaged. This version is based on the 3.4 release and includes
      the <strong>SOAP</strong> proxy.
      On top of that, it provides a totally refactored <strong>message
      persistence</strong> management.
      </p>
      <p>The latest 3.4 update (joram3_4_3) has also been packaged.</p>
      <p>JORAM is now released under the <strong>LGPL</strong> licence.</p>

      <subtitle>March 19th, 2003: new JORAM releases.</subtitle>
      <p>JORAM 3.3 is now available as a packaged version.
     As a reminder, it provides a new administration implementation. In CVS it
     is now tagged joram3_3_1. Compared to joram3_3_0, it is a maintenance
     version, correcting a few bugs.
     </p>
      <p>JORAM 3.4 is available only in the CVS distribution. This
     release tagged joram3_4_0 supports the SOAP protocol as a link between
     a Joram client and a Joram platform. It rearchitectures the JMS proxy
     server side, and the JMS connection client side, for supporting multiple 
     protocols (currently TCP and SOAP).</p>

      <subtitle>December 11th, 2002: a new JORAM version tagged 3_3_0 is
      available in the CVS distribution.</subtitle>
      <p>This new version provides a totally refactored <strong>administration</strong> 
      protocol. Administration is now based on JMS communication and is much
      more flexible than the past implementation. Hopefully it will make
      contributing easier; JORAM's administration still misses graphical tools
      and JMX support, and any contribution would be highly appreciated.
      </p>
      <p>This new administration implementation comes with a new administration
      interface. Old administration codes should go on working even if they now
      use deprecated methods. 
      </p>

     <subtitle>October 21st, 2002: JORAM 3.2 provides new features!</subtitle>
      <p>The main added values of Joram 3.2.0 are the new implementations of
         <strong>hierarchical topics</strong> and <strong>dead message queues</strong>.
      </p>
      <p>According to the JMS specification, topics might have a hierarchical
         structure allowing clients to subscribe or publish to given subtopics.
         Joram's fully distributed structure allows a topic hierarchy to be
         spread over many servers.
      </p>
      <p>A dead message queue is a destination getting undeliverable messages.
         Messages might be considered undeliverable because they expired 
         before delivery, because they were sent on a non accessible
         destination or because they are constantly denied when consumed.
      </p>
      <p>This new version also provides a <strong>flow control mechanism</strong> in
         order to prevent a Joram platform to be overloaded by a heavily
         producing client.
      </p>

     <subtitle>June 10th, 2002: JORAM now implements the new JMS 1.1
        specification!</subtitle>
      <p><strong>Joram 3.1.0 fully implements JMS 1.1</strong> providing unified
        messaging interfaces for the Point-to-Point and Pub/Sub
        domains. In the previous versions of Joram and JMS, the
        client programming model made a strong distinction between
        these two domains. Now, the domain unification simplifies
        the model and allows to include PTP and Pub/Sub messaging in
        a same transaction.</p>
      <p>No need to modify existing applications: code written for
        the previous Joram and JMS versions will work as is with
        these new versions.</p>
      

      <subtitle>7th june 2002: JORAM 3.0.4 available (cvs tag: joram3_0_4-1)</subtitle>
      
      <p>
        This version is a maintenance version of JORAM, it includes
        corrections of bugs in XA and ASF classes. 
        The JORAM CVS repository has been branched after this release:
        next version of JORAM will implement JMS 1.1. The branch
        corresponding to JMS 1.0.2b is jms1_0_2b. 
      </p>


      <subtitle>26th March 2002: JORAM 3.0.1 available (cvs tag: joram3_0_1)</subtitle>
      
      <p>
	This version corrects all bugs discovered by JORAM community
	since the release of JORAM 3.0.0. These corrections were already available
	in CVS repository.
      </p>


      <subtitle>20th March 2002: JMS Test Suite released</subtitle>

      <p><strong>A JMS Test Suite</strong> has been released under LGPL.<br />
	This suite tests JMS features. All code of the test suite is
	pure JMS without any dependency to JORAM.</p>

      <subtitle>11th March 2002: JORAM 3.0.0 available (cvs tag: joram3_0_0)</subtitle>
      
      <p>
	Compared to JORAM previous versions, this new release is a complete
	re-factoring of the code base. It gets rid of the
	previous limitations and defects. The JMS specification is now fully
	implemented, JORAM provides authentication and security
	features, and introduces a distributed implementation of the Topic
	destination. Its clean and sound code basis guarantees fast
	and easy future developements and enhancements.<br/>
	A suite of tests based on JUnit will be very soon proposed for
	download.
      </p>
      

      <subtitle>16th January 2002: JORAM 2.2 (cvs tag:
	joram2_2)</subtitle>
      <p>This version adds support for Ant build
	system.
      </p>


      <subtitle>14th September 2001: JORAM 2.1.1 (cvs tag: joram2_1_1)</subtitle>
    
      <p>This version corrects some bugs concerning the selectors. <code>Null</code>
      selectors are now authorized, syntax is systematically checked and Strings
      syntax has been enlarged to characters such as '/', ';', ...</p>


      <subtitle>31st August 2001: JORAM 2.1.0 (cvs tag: joram2_1_0)</subtitle>

      <ul>
	<li><strong>New feature:</strong> message selection (see JMS spec section 3.8).</li>
	<li><strong>Bug:</strong> the problem when sending objects not "known" by the agents
	  server inside an ObjectMessage does not occur anymore. No need now to add this
	  object's class in the agents server classpath.</li>
      </ul>
      
      
      <subtitle>15th May 2001: JORAM 2.0.1 (cvs tag: joram2_0_1)</subtitle>
      
      <p>This version closely follows the 2.0.0 and provides improvements in the
	management of closing sockets, and a better handling of stopping threads when
	closing <code>Sessions</code>, <code>ConnectionConsumers</code> and <code>Connections</code>.</p>
      
      
      <subtitle>7th May 2001: JORAM 2.0.0 (cvs tag: joram2_0_0) fully implements the
	Application Server Facilities (ASF)</subtitle>
      
      <ul>
	<li><strong>New features</strong>: ASF part of the specification, synchronous reception on topics
	  and asynchronous reception on queues have been implemented.</li>
	<li>JORAM and JOnAS provide <strong>Message Driven Beans</strong> support.</li>
	<li><strong>Bugs</strong> have been fixed: <code>ConnectionFactories</code> accept now more than one active
	  Connection at a time, and problems while running JORAM under Solaris are
	  solved.</li>
      </ul>
      
      
      <subtitle>5th December 2000: JORAM included in JOnAS</subtitle>
      
      <p>JOnAS tagged <strong>2.2.2</strong> includes JORAM in its distribution. JOnAS 2.2.2 / JORAM
	1.1.0 allow using JMS from Enterprise Java Beans and have been successfully
	tested on AIX, Linux, Solaris, NT and Windows 2000.</p>
      
      
      <subtitle>10th October 2000: JORAM is now tagged 1.1.0 (cvs tag: joram1_1_0)</subtitle>
      
      <ul>
	<li><strong>New feature:</strong> JORAM now includes a <strong>JNDI</strong> "light" implementation (JNDI 1.1.2).</li>

	<li><strong>XA</strong> classes have been successfully tested through 
        JOnAS EJB implementation.</li>

	<li>Persistence and lookup <strong>bugs</strong> fixed.</li>
      </ul>
      
      <subtitle>31st August 2000 : JORAM implements more</subtitle>
      
      <ul>
	<li><strong>XA</strong> classes, allowing JMS operations to be involved in a distributed
	  transaction, are available.</li>
	<li><strong>Transacted</strong> mode completed.</li>
	<li>External <strong>JNDI</strong> now usable.</li>
      </ul>
      

      <subtitle>26th May 2000 : JORAM first open source version available !</subtitle>

      
    </s1>
  </body>

</document>
      