<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM '../../common/dtd/objectweb.dtd'>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="joram-team@ow2.org">JORAM team</author>
    <title>Home Page</title>
    <filename>index.xml</filename>
    <pathtoroot>.</pathtoroot>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <s1 name="JORAM: Java (TM) Open Reliable Asynchronous Messaging">

    <table border="0" width="100%">
  	<tr>
	  <td align="left" rowspan="2">
	      <img src="images/joram.png" alt="JORAM Logo" height="140" width="300" border="0" hspace="2"/>
      </td>
	  <td align="right"><script type="text/javascript" src="http://www.ohloh.net/p/4238/widgets/project_thin_badge.js"></script></td>
	</tr>
  	<tr>
	  <td align="left">
	    <p>JORAM has been made available for download since May 2000.<br></br>
        As a standalone software, JORAM has been downloaded more than 100,000 times.</p>
	  </td>
	</tr>
    </table>
    
    </s1>
    
    <s1 name="Introduction">
      
      <p><strong>JORAM</strong> incorporates a 100% pure Java implementation of <strong>JMS 1.1</strong>
      (Java Message Service API released by Sun Microsystem, Inc.) specification.<br></br>
      It provides access to a really distributed MOM (Message Oriented Middleware), built on top of the
      <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/">ScalAgent D.T.</a> agents based platform.</p>
      
      <p>JORAM is a mature project started in 1999, it is an <strong>open source</strong> software released under
      the <strong>LGPL</strong> license since May 2000.<br></br>
      It provides a production ready distributed MOM already used within many critical operational applications.</p>

      <p>Joram is now designed with an OSGi<sup>TM</sup> based services architecture to provide a dynamically adaptable
      messaging server:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>The Joram server can be launched as a set of OSGi bundles (it is always possible to launch the server as
        a classic Java program).</li>
        <li>Additional services can be started, stopped, reconfigured: Command line interface, Web console, etc.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Stable versions of JORAM are JMS 1.1 certified. Moreover JORAM is used by JOnAS to undergo the Java EE
      certification, and has passed all tests concerning JMS certification in this J2EE TCK.<br></br>
      Professional Support and training are available from
      <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/en/joram-33/services-35/support">Scalagent D.T.</a>.</p>
 
    </s1>
   
    <s1 name="Latest News">

      <s2 name="February 19, 2014: Eclipse IoT Day Grenoble 2014 conference, France.">
      <p><a href="www.scalagent.com">ScalAgent D.T.</a>) is currently implementing version 3.1 of
      the MQTT protocol. This work is to be presented by David Féliot at the
      <a href="http://wiki.eclipse.org/Eclipse_IoT_Day_Grenoble_2014">Eclipse IoT Day Grenoble 2014 conference</a>,
      organised by Eclipse at Grenoble on the 19th of february 2014.</p>
      <p>David's presentation will be available on the <a href="http://mqtt.jorammq.com/">ScalAgent's MQTT</a> web
      page after the conference.</p>
      </s2>

      <s2 name="November 13, 2013: OW2 Annual Conference, Paris, France.">
      <p>Serge Lacourte, CEO of ScalAgent DT, participates to a panel at the annual OW2 conference
	  on the subject : Benefits and challenges of integrating open source components.</p>
      </s2>
      
      <s2 name="October 2, 2013: JORAM 5.9.0 release is available.">
      <p>This release introduces many improvements and bug fixes, essentially:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Implementation of JMS 2.0 specification:<ul>
            <li>Open-source implementation of new API.</li>
            <li>Implementation of the updated specification.</li>
          </ul>
          All functions of the new JMS 2.0 specification are now implemented except the shared subscriptions.
          Currently Joram succeeds 98% of the compliance tests for the specification 2.0.
        </li>
        <li>An significant work to optimize the performances, among other things:<ul>
            <li>A new marshalling framewwork.</li>
            <li>An optimized handling of connections and marshalling.</li>
            <li>Optional message compression.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>A Xoram component (C/C++ client API), corrected and updated.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>This version is available for <a href="http://joram.ow2.org/download/index.html">download</a>,
      and in Maven repository.</p>
      <p>It is tagged in SVN (JORAM_5_9_0), the complete list of changes can be viewed either in
      <a href="dev/versions.html">code updates</a> or in
      <a href="http://websvn.ow2.org/log.php?repname=joram&amp;path=%2Ftrunk%2Fjoram%2F&amp;isdir=1&amp;">SVN history</a>.</p>
      </s2>

      <s2 name="April 17, 2013: Have fun using Joram on Raspberry PI with Java 8.">
      <p>Joram requires very few resources to run, this simple tutorial shows how to launch
      a Joram server on a Raspberry PI and test it.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>First you need a <a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org/">Raspberry PI</a> with Java 8, you can
        find documentation instructions to setup JDK 8 on a Raspberry Pi device
        <a href="http://jdk8.java.net/fxarmpreview/javafx-arm-developer-preview.html">here</a>.
        </li>
        <li>Second download a <a href="http://bamboo.ow2.org/artifact/JORAM-ANT/JOB1/build-latest/Releases/release/target/joram-release-5.9.1-SNAPSHOT.zip">snapshot</a>
        of Joram's distribution, then unzip it on your Raspberry PI.
        </li>
        <li>Third, follow the tutorial instructions : <a href="doc/tutorials/raspberry/raspberry.htm">here</a>.</li>
      </ul>
      </s2>
   
      <s2 name="January 14 2013: JORAM 5.8.1 maintenance release is available.">
      <p>This release introduces somes improvements and bug fixes, essentially:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Handles connection close when transmitting large messages between servers (JORAM-62).</li>
        <li>Best handle of JMS connection loss (JORAM-84).</li>
        <li>Removes useless connection cleaning tasks (JORAM-87).</li>
        <li>Unsubscribe Connection and Session MBeans to avoid memory leak (JORAM-99).</li>
        <li>Fixes potential bug with the cleaning mechanism of client context in the MOM (JORAM-68).</li>
        <li>Factorizes the client timer for any JMS connection (JORAM-69).</li>
        <li>Adds syncExceptionOnFull option (JORAM-101).</li>
        <li>Spring intégration and OSGi configuration (DnD).</li>
      </ul>
      <p>This version is tagged in SVN (JORAM_5_8_1) and is available in Maven repository.</p>
      <p>The complete list of changes can be viewed either in
      <a href="http://websvn.ow2.org/filedetails.php?repname=joram&amp;path=%2Ftrunk%2Fjoram%2Fhistory">SVN history</a>.</p>
      </s2>
      
      <s2 name="October 24, 2012: Optimal JORAM performance reports.">
      <p>The <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/en/mqperf-69/produits-70/presentation-370">MQPerf</a> service
      helps you to understand the behavior of your application using Joram, and enables you to find out Joram
      optimal performances on your own system, without paying the necessary cost in terms of skill development
      and work load.</p>
       
      <p><a href="http://www.scalagent.com/en/mqperf-69/produits-70/presentation-370">MQPerf</a> is very easy to
      execute, it requires only 5 mns of your time to get a free performance report. Please have a look at this
      service at  <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/en/mqperf-69/produits-70/presentation-370">ScalAgent D.T.</a>,
      test it as much as you want and let us know how you like it. You may also use our new
      <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/forum/">forum</a>, dedicated to MQPerf, for any question about this
      service.</p>
      </s2>

      <s2 name="October 23, 2012: JORAM 5.8.0 release is available.">
      <p>This release introduces many improvements and bug fixes, essentially:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Refactoring of the JCA resource adapter allowing to deploy many resource adapter
          in an application server. This enhanced JCA connector includes a new configuration
          mechanism allowing user friendly configuration.
        </li>
        <li>Enhancements of the JMS bridge.</li>
        <li>Enhancements of the AMQP bridge.</li>
        <li>Adds an individual acknowledge mode in addition to JMS specification.</li>
        <li>Joram's MBeans extension.</li>
        <li>Adds a specific logger allowing to trace message sending and receiving client side.</li>
        <li>
          Adds specific ConnectionFactory elements, these factories can be used either
          through the administration API or the XML configuration scripts. Factory parameters
          can now be defined in XML configuration scripts.
        </li>
        <li>
          Adds specific factories for specialized destination:<ul>
            <li>Mail acquisition and distribution destinations.</li>
            <li>FTP queue.</li>
            <li>Monitoring queue and topic.</li>
            <li>Collector queue and topic.</li>
            <li>SchedulerQueue.</li>
            <li>JMS and AMQP bridges.</li>
          </ul>
          These factories can be used either through the administration API or the XML
          configuration scripts.
        </li>
        <li>
          Allows the configuration of the JMS and AMQP bridge connection services:<ul>
            <li>Add elements to define either an AMQP or JMS bridge connection to a Joram server
            through the XML cpnfiguration scripts.</li>
            <li>Add methods to add or delete either an AMQP or JMS bridge connection to a Joram
            server through the administration API.</li>
          </ul>
		  Use URLs to describes each connection factory. 
        </li>
        <li>Fix LGPL license removing unapropriate ASF.</li>
        <li>A Xoram component (C/C++ client API), corrected and updated.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>This version is available for <a href="http://joram.ow2.org/download/index.html">download</a>,
      and in Maven repository.</p>
      <p>It is tagged in SVN (JORAM_5_8_0), the complete list of changes can be viewed either in
      <a href="dev/versions.html">code updates</a> or in
      <a href="http://websvn.ow2.org/filedetails.php?repname=joram&amp;path=%2Ftrunk%2Fjoram%2Fhistory">SVN history</a>.</p>
      </s2>

      <s2 name="October 10, 2011: 2 new tutorials are available.">
      <p>Two short tutorials are available in the <a href="doc/tutorials.html">tutorial</a> section. The first
      shows the use of the web administration console of Joram and the second allows benchmarking of Joram.</p>
      </s2>
    
      <s2 name="October 03, 2011: JORAM JMX/JMS Connector tutorial is available.">
      <p>A short tutorial demonstrating the use of JORAM JMX/JMS connector is available in the
      <a href="doc/tutorials.html">tutorial</a> section.</p>
      </s2>

      <s2 name="July 13, 2011: JORAM/AMQP 1.0 is released">
      <p>Joram team is proud to announce the final version of the implementation of the specification AMQP v0.9.1.
      This version successfully passed interoperability testing with RabbitMQ and QPID, it is available in Maven
      reprository.</p>
      </s2>

      <s2 name="November 24-25, 2010: OW2 Annual Conference, Paris, France.">
      <p>During the <a href="http://www.ow2.org/view/Events/OW2AnnualConference2010">OW2 Annual Conference</a>,
      Serge Lacourte (<a href="www.scalagent.com">ScalAgent D.T.</a>) presents two very different Use Cases of Joram.
      They demonstrate the ability of Joram to adapt to very different deployment environments,
      thanks to the very high configuration capability of its architecture.</p>
      <p>
      The slide show is available on the OW2 web site:
      <a href="http://www.ow2.org/xwiki/bin/download/Events2010AnnualConference/Program/JORAM-S-Lacourte.pdf">Configuration from clustering to WAN distribution with Joram</a>.
			</p>
      </s2>

      <s2 name="May 18, 2010: JORAM Architecture Designer plugin 1.0.0 is available">
      <p>The first official release of Joram Architecture Designer plugin for Eclipse is available
      for <a href="http://joram.ow2.org/download/index.html">download</a> (package JORAM_DESIGNER at
      the end of the page). A brief PDF installation guide is available for download.</p>
      <p>As described in the <a href="http://joram.ow2.org/doc/tutorials.html">tutorial</a> the designer
      allows to graphically build a Joram distributed architecture. It produces <code>a3servers.xml</code>
      and <code>joramAdmin.xml</code> configuration files. Now, it allows to automatically deploy the
      designed configuration using <a href="http://fdf.gforge.inria.fr/">DeployWare</a>.</p>
      <p>This release is tagged in SVN (JORAM_DESIGNER_1_0_0).</p>
      </s2>

      <s2 name="May 10, 2010: JORAM in OW2 Open Source Cloudware Initiative.">
      <p>Last week, OW2 Consortium members Bull, Orange and INRIA had announced the OW2 Open Source Cloudware Initiative
      at the Solutions Datacenter Management and Cloud Computing trade show in Paris. The bedrock of the OSC Initiative
      includes the following open source OW2 projects: CLIF, Entropy, JASMINe, JOnAS, and <strong>JORAM</strong> to provide
      the capability for on-demand JavaEE autonomic server provisioning according to demand fluctuations and ProActive for
      complementary heterogeneous capacity management.</p>
      <p>See the Cloudware Initiative Press Release in
      <a href="http://www.ow2.org/xwiki/bin/download/Cloud/WebHome/OW2CloudInitiative%2DPR%2Dlong%2DenV3.6.pdf">English</a> and in
      <a href="http://www.ow2.org/xwiki/bin/download/Cloud/WebHome/OW2CloudInitiative%2DPR%2Dlong%2Dfrv3.6.pdf">French</a></p>
      </s2>
    
      <s2 name="March 09, 2010: Joram successfully passes performance and scalability tests for SM&amp;C.">
      <p>The CNES implementation of a new generation of Spacecraft Monitoring and Control system (CCSDS SM&amp;C stantard)
      foresee to use Joram as underlying communication middleware. Performance and scalability tests have been conducted
      successfully to validate this future usage of Joram.</p>
      <p>Credits to HP &amp; <a href="http://www.oxalya.com">Oxalya</a> and their Minalogic partnership for their support
      in granting access to the 'virtual nodes' cluster.</p>
      </s2>
      
      <s2 name="January 25, 2010: joram-commits@ow2.org">
      <p>A new mailing-list is now available, it allows to follow all the modifications on the Joram's SVN.</p>
      <p>You can subscribe at <a href="http://mail.ow2.org/wws/arc/joram-commits">joram-commits@ow2.org</a>.</p>
      </s2>
            
	    <s2 name="December 2nd and 3rd, 2009: JORAM Training Session, Grenoble, France">
	      <p>A two-day training session about JORAM is scheduled in Grenoble; it will be delivered in french language.</p>
	      <p>The session is entitled "Design and Deploy a Distributed JORAM Messaging System".</p>
	      <p>This training session is targeted at architects and system designers that intend to integrate  the JORAM component
	      within a global distributed solution. It includes a significant part of  experimentations and case studies based on
	      real-world application scenarios.</p>
	      <p>The session is conducted by ScalAgent Distributed Technologies, the leading developer of the JORAM component. We
	      offer to share our expertise through a training session aiming at providing the key knowledge to use and deploy a JORAM
	      system that fits your own requirements. This two-day session details the design principles of JORAM and describes the
	      best practices that will enable to take advantage of its advanced properties for complex networked environments.</p>
	      <p>Detailed information about this training session is available online
	      <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/spip.php?article314 ">(PDF, in french only)</a></p>
      </s2>
       
      <s2 name="October 16, 2009: Joram Snapshot are now available">
      <p>The latest development snapshots are now available from
      <a href="http://bamboo.ow2.org/artifact/JORAM-ANT/JOB1/build-latest/Releases/release/target">Continuous Integration Build Tool</a>.
      This will be built automatically from the current development code after each change in the SVN code base.</p>
      <p>If you need quickly a fix for a particular bug, you may be able to find a fixed Joram release here well
      before the fix makes it into the next release version. On the other hand, these snapshots might sometimes
      be unstable.</p>
      </s2>
			
      <s2 name="January 18, 2006">
        <p>JORAM is acknowledged as the best open source MOM implementation, according to
        <a href="http://java.sys-con.com/node/171304">JDJ's readers</a>, challenging
        proprietary products from IBM, Sun and TIBCO.</p>
      </s2>

	    <s2 name="September 26th, 2005: JORAM Survey Synthesis">
	      <p>A synthesis of the JORAM Survey is available <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/IMG/pdf/050926-JORAM_Survey-Synthesis-2.pdf">here</a>.</p>
 	      <p>Several users have expressed their need for various forms of services (support, consulting, training, etc.).
        Therefore we would like to remind that a description of professional services on JORAM is available 
        <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/spip.php?article41">here</a>.
        Do not hesitate to contact us for any further question you may have on JORAM :
        <a href="mailto:contact@scalagent.com">contact@scalagent.com</a>.</p>
      </s2>

      <subtitle><a href="history.html">All the News</a></subtitle>
    </s1>

  </body>
</document>
