<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM '../../common/dtd/objectweb.dtd'>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="joram-team@objectweb.org">JORAM team</author>
    <title>Home Page</title>
    <filename>index.xml</filename>
    <pathtoroot>.</pathtoroot>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <s1 name="Latest News">
			<subtitle>November 9, 2004: JORAM 4.1.2 maintenance release is available</subtitle>
			<p>Joram 4.1.2 is a maintenance release with bug fixes and performance improvments. This version is embedded in the last JOnAS build (4.2.0)</p>
		  <subtitle>October 13, 2004: JORAM 4.1.1 maintenance release is available</subtitle>
			<p>Joram 4.1.1 is a maintenance release with bug fixes and updates of the underlying network communication system.</p>
			<subtitle>September 14, 2004: JORAM 4.1 is available</subtitle>
			<p>Joram 4.1 is finally available for download. It provides the following new features as well
			 as fixes and improvements : </p>
			 <ul>
			 <li>The Joram 4.1 JCA 1.5 RA, handles:
			 <ul>
			 <li>Inbound (asynchronous message flow) and Outbound (synchronous message flow) communications</li>
			 <li>Support of distributed (XA) and local transactions.</li>
			 <li>Automatic recovery of indoubt Xids via XAResource.recover().</li> 
			 <li>Deployment as a Resource Adapter to an external JORAM server.</li>
			 <li>Deployment in collocated mode : a JORAM server is started and stopped at RA deployment and undeployment.
			 </li>
			 </ul>
			 </li>
			 <li>The clustered queue feature provides a load-balancing mechanism. It is made up of several queues
			  exchanging messages depending on their load. This new feature is sponsored by France Telecom R&amp;D,
				as will be the future High-Availability Joram server to be released in the next version. </li>
			 </ul>
			 <p>JORAM 4.1 is used by JOnAS to undergo the J2EE 1.4 certification, and has already passed all tests 
			 concerning JMS in this TCK.</p>
			 <p>The new packages are available in the <a href="download/index.html">download area</a>. The CVS tag is 
			 joram4_1_0 (<a href="http://forge.objectweb.org/cvs/?group_id=4">CVS repository</a>).</p>
			 <p>The documentation has also been deeply updated with a new all-in-one manual.</p>
		
			<subtitle>October 20-21: JORAM Training Session, Grenoble, France</subtitle>
			<p>A two-day training session on JORAM is scheduled and will be delivered in french language.
			 The session is entitled "Design and Deploy a Distributed JORAM Messaging System".</p>
		  <p>This training session is targeted at architects and system designers that intend to integrate 
			the JORAM component within a global distributed solution. It includes a significant part of 
			experimentations and case studies based on real-world application scenarios.</p>
			<p>The session is conducted by ScalAgent Distributed Technologies, the leading developer 
			of the JORAM component. We offer to share our expertise through a training session that provides
			 the key knowledge to use and deploy a JORAM system that fits your requirements.
			This two-day session details the design principles of JORAM and describes the best practices 
			to take advantage of its advanced properties in complex networked environments.</p>
			<p>Detailed information about this training session is available online 
			<a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/fr/datasheet/040820-JORAM-formation.pdf">(PDF, in french only)</a></p>
      <subtitle>July 1st, 2004: Report of the 1st JORAM Users' Day</subtitle>
  	  <p>The first JORAM Users' Day has been held last June 17 th in Paris.
			 This event was the first successful attempt within the ObjectWeb community 
			 to have direct exchanges between users and designers/developers of an 
			 ObjectWeb component.</p>
			 <p>The Report as well as some of the presentations are available online at
			  the ScalAgent Distributed Technologies web site : </p>
			 <ul>
			 <li>Report as <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/products/joram-userday040617-report.htm">HTML</a>
			  or <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/datasheet/040617-JORAM-Day-report.pdf">PDF</a></li>
			 <li><a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/datasheet/040617-JoramDay-Intro-UK.pdf">
			 Introduction by Roland Balter (ScalAgent Distributed Technologies)(PDF)</a>
			 </li>
       <li><a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/datasheet/040617-ObjectWeb-Joram.pdf">
			 Next Generation Open Source by J.P. Laisné (President of the 
			 Objectweb consortium)(PDF in french)</a>
			 </li>
       <li><a href="http://www.scalagent.com/pages/en/datasheet/040617-EPFL-joram_day.pdf">
			 JMSGroups: Towards JMS-Compliant Group Communication by A. Kupsys 
			 (EPFL Switzerland) (PDF)</a>
			 </li>
			 </ul>
			 <p>The discussion about JORAM is open especially for those who have not been
			 able to join the Users' Day. Any contribution is welcome on the main
			 JORAM mailing list.</p>
    </s1>

    <s1 name="JORAM: Java (TM) Open Reliable Asynchronous Messaging">

      <subtitle>As a standalone software, JORAM has been downloaded
                more than 22,000 times</subtitle>

      <table border="0">
	<tr>
	  <td><img src="images/joram.jpg" alt="JORAM logo" height="132"
               width="287" border="0" hspace="2"/></td>
	  <td valign="middle"><p>Current packaged release: 4.1.0</p>
	                      <p>Latest CVS tag: JORAM_4_1_0</p></td>
	</tr>
      </table>
      
      <p><strong>JORAM</strong> incorporates a 100% pure Java
      implementation of <strong>JMS</strong> (Java Message Service API
      released by Sun Microsystem, Inc.). It provides access to a MOM
      (Message Oriented Middleware), built on top of the <a
      href="http://www.scalagent.com/">ScalAgent</a> agents based
      distributed platform.</p>
      <p> JORAM, the MOM it gives access to and the Scalagent
      platform are <strong>open source</strong> softwares and released under
      the <strong>LGPL</strong> license.</p>
      <!--/s2-->

      <s2 name="Specification">

        <p>JORAM provides full support to <strong>JMS 1.1</strong>:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Unified interfaces for the Point-to-Point (PTP) and
            Publish/Subscribe (Pub/Sub) messaging models</li>
          <li><strong>AND</strong> still the semantically specific PTP and
            Pub/Sub interfaces</li>
          <li>Full backward compatibility with JMS 1.0.2b compliant
            applications</li>
          <li>Local, TCP and SOAP (HTTP/XML) client-server communication
              protocols</li>
          <li>Message persistence and guarantee of delivery</li>
          <li>Hierarchical topics</li>
          <li>Message selection</li>
          <li>Message prioritization</li>
					<li>A JCA 1.5 Resource Adapter</li>
        </ul>
        <p>JORAM also includes the following extra-features:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>A persistent, reliable and distributed JNDI server</li>
          <li>A configurable dead message queue</li>
          <li>Load balancing through clustered topics and queues</li>
          <li>Monitoring methods</li>
          <li>A bridge feature allowing to link JORAM to any JMS compliant
              messaging platform</li>
          <li>Client libraries allowing J2ME applications to
          access the JORAM platform in a JMS 1.1 "way"</li>
          <li>A graphical administration and monitoring tool</li>
        </ul>
      </s2>

      <s2 name="Getting Involved">
	
	<p>Any input or personal view for improving and/or developing
	JORAM is welcome. JORAM, as an <strong>open source</strong> project,
	also welcomes <strong>external contributions</strong>. Interested?
	Contact <a
	href="mailto:joram-team@objectweb.org">us</a> or check the
        <a href="dev/corner.html">developer's corner</a>.
        </p>

      </s2>  
    </s1>
    
  </body>

</document>
