<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM '../../common/dtd/objectweb.dtd'>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="joram-team@objectweb.org">JORAM team</author>
    <title>Partners</title>
    <filename>partners.xml</filename>
    <pathtoroot>.</pathtoroot>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <s1 name="Current partners">
    <table>	
    <tr>
      <td align="center" valign="middle">
      <a href="http://www.bull.com/">
      <img src="images/partners/bull.jpg" alt="Bull logo" border="0"
           height="67" width="210"/></a>
      </td>
      <td>
      <p><a href="http://www.bull.com">Bull</a> is one of the main
      contributors of the JORAM open source JMS
      messaging platform. Bull is an international IT group that specialises
      in designing, developing and implementing secure IT infrastructures.
      Bull is dedicated to helping customers transform their processes and
      infrastructures in order to take full advantage of information
      technology to drive their market growth. To reach this objective, Bull
      provides a complete offer that includes not only IT services, from
      consulting to systems integration and outsourcing but also the design
      and development of infrastructure solutions, with particular emphasis
      on servers, storage and secure management software. Bull has gained
      strong recognition in the major economic sectors, such as, the public
      sector, finance, industry and telecommunications.</p>
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td align="center" valign="middle">
      <a href="http://www.scalagent.com/">
      <img src="images/partners/scalagent.jpg" alt="ScalAgent logo"
        border="0" width="295" height="101"/></a>
      </td>
      <td align="left" valign="middle">
      <p><a href="http://www.scalagent.com/">ScalAgent Distributed
      Technologies</a> is a startup company spin-off from 
      <a href="http://www.inria.fr/">INRIA</a> and
      <a href="http://www.bull.com/">Bull</a>, which aims at developing and
      market advanced mediation solutions for large-scale Internet business
      infrastructure and applications. Scalagent is the main developer and
      integrator for JORAM.</p>
      </td>
    </tr>
    </table>

    </s1>

    <s1 name="Initial partners">
    <table>	
    <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle">
    <img src="images/partners/dyade.gif" alt="Dyade logo" width="270"
         border="0" height="65"/>
    </td>
    <td><p>The G.I.E. ("Groupement d'Int&#233;r&#234;t &#201;conomique")
    Dyade was a BULL/INRIA advanced
    research joint venture. Its goals was the conception and development
    of new technological components for future information systems.</p>
    </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" valign="middle" align="center">
    <a href="http://www.inria.fr/">
    <img src="images/partners/inria.gif" border="0" width="166"
         height="45" alt="INRIA logo" align="middle"/></a>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" valign="middle" align="left">
    <a href="http://www.inria.fr/">INRIA</a> is the French National
    Institute for Research in Computer Science and Control. It is
    a scientific and technological institute operating under the
    dual authority of the Ministry of Research and the Ministry
    of Industry.</td>
    </tr>
    </table>
    </s1>
    
  </body>

</document>
